<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- If further character entities are required then they should be added to the DOCTYPE above.
     Use of an external entity file is not recommended. -->

<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="std"
  docName="draft-ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-message-key-03"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates=""
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="YANG Message Keys"> YANG Message Keys for
     Message Broker Integration</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-message-key-03"/>

    <author fullname="Thomas Graf" initials="TG" surname="Graf">

      <organization>Swisscom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Binzring 17</street>
          <city>Zurich</city>
          <code>8045</code>
          <country>CH</country>
        </postal>
        <email>thomas.graf@swisscom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ahmed Elhassany" initials="AE" surname="Elhassany">

      <organization>Swisscom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Binzring 17</street>
          <city>Zurich</city>
          <code>8045</code>
          <country>CH</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ahmed.elhassany@swisscom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Alex Huang Feng" initials="AHF" surname="Huang Feng">

      <organization>INSA-Lyon</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Lyon</city>
          <country>FR</country>
        </postal>
        <email>alex.huang-feng@insa-lyon.fr</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Benoît Claise" initials="BC" surname="Claise">

    <organization>Everything OPS</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Liege</city>
          <country>BE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>benoit@everything-ops.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Paolo Lucente" initials="PL" surname="Lucente">

      <organization>NTT</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Veemweg 23</street>
          <city>Barneveld</city>
          <code>3771</code>
          <country>NL</country>
        </postal>
        <email>paolo@ntt.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="23" month="June" year="2026"/>

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>NMOP</workgroup>
    <keyword>YANG-Push</keyword>
    <keyword>Data Mesh</keyword>
    <keyword>Network Telemetry</keyword>
    <keyword>Network Analytics</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies a mechanism to define a unique Message
      key for a YANG to Message Broker integration and a topic
      addressing scheme based on YANG-Push subscription type and YANG
      Schema Node Identifier. This enables YANG data consumption
      of a subset of subscribed YANG data, either per specific YANG
      data node, identifier or telemetry message type, by indexing and
      organizing in Message Broker topics. It helps to index the
      information by using data taxonomy and organizes data in
      partitions and shards of Message Brokers and time series
      databases.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="Introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>Nowadays network operators are using machine and human
      readable <xref target="RFC7950">YANG</xref> to model their
      configurations and monitor YANG operational data from
      their networks according to <xref target="Mar24"/>.</t>

      <t>Most network analytic use cases require real-time data and the
      delivery of near real-time analytical and actionable insights.
      This imposes high scalability, resilience and low overhead in the
      data processing pipeline. Accessing the right data for the right
      use case with minimal overhead and in the shortest period of time
      is therefore crucial.</t>

      <t>Network operators organize their data in a <xref
      target="Deh22">Data Mesh</xref> according to <xref
      target="Bod24"/> where a Message Broker, such as <xref
      target="Kaf11">Apache Kafka</xref> or <xref target="Pul16">Apache
      Pulsar</xref>, facilitates the exchange of Messages among data
      processing components in topics and subjects. Typically, data is
      being stored in Message Broker topics for several hours or days
      to facilitate resilience in the data processing chain and
      addressed in Subjects depending on Schema, enabling a data
      consumer to address and re-consume previously consumed data again
      if previously lost.</t>

      <t>Dimensional data is structured information in a data store.
      It uses a model of dimension tables to organize business metrics
      and their descriptive context. This model, developed by <xref
      target="Kim96">Ralph Kimball</xref>, simplifies data analysis and
      reporting by creating denormalized, easy-to-understand structures
      for quick querying. It is optimized for online analytical
      processing (OLAP) and data warehouses by using the data taxonomy
      to scale in partitions and shards. <xref
      target="RFC7950">YANG</xref> as a data modelling language
      based on hierarchical tree-based structures facilitates the
      modelling of dimensional data. This is best shown with <xref
      target="RFC8340">YANG Tree Diagrams</xref>.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration">An
      Architecture for YANG-Push to Message Broker Integration</xref>
      specifies an architecture for integrating YANG-Push with
      Message Brokers for a Data Mesh architecture. <xref section="4.5"
      sectionFormat="of"
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration"/> describes
      how the notification messages at a YANG-Push Receiver are being
      transformed to the Message Broker while <xref section="3"
      sectionFormat="of"
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message"/>
      specifies to a Message Schema to contextualize telemetry data.
      However, neither of these documents addresses how these messages
      should be indexed in a Message Broker, nor define how topics,
      partitioning and sharding must be used.</t>

      <t>Due to this missing dimensional indexing for Message Broker
      stored YANG data, all YANG data is stored in one single Topic.
      This leads to a round robin distribution across multiple
      Partitions where each YANG Schema ID is defined as a subject
      within that topic. Therefore, the entire Topic from all Partitions
      needs to be consumed first before data selection can be applied.
      This leads to avoidable data processing overhead which in turn
      impairs scalability and real-time capabilities, required for
      certain Network Analytics use cases.</t>

      <t>YANG telemetry data can be used for several network analytic use
      cases. Importantly, depending on the use case, only a subset of
      the subscribed YANG data might be necessary (in time or space).
      For example, for specific use cases, it is more important to know
      the current network state, as opposed to have the full series of
      the state changes over time. In other use cases, instead of
      consuming data for all network nodes, only a specific network node
      or network node component requires the YANG monitoring and hence
      subscription.</t>

      <t>This document defines how YANG Messages <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message"/> should
      be indexed and organized in Message Broker topics by leveraging
      the network node hostname, the YANG-Push subscription identifier,
      and concrete XPath data node instances derived from the YANG
      schema path for indexing. Then, a YANG-Push subscription type and
      YANG Schema name for a Message Broker topic naming scheme is
      defined to better organize YANG data.</t>

      <t>Network node hostname and subtree and xpath filters are part
      of "ietf-yang-push-telemetry-message" structured YANG data
      defined in <xref section="3" sectionFormat="of"
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message"/>. The
      Message Key is derived through a three-phase algorithm that
      normalizes subscription filters against the YANG schema path and
      extracts concrete data node instances from each notification
      message.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Conventions_and_Definitions">
      <name>Conventions and Definitions</name>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",
      "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to
      be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
      <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
      capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <section anchor="Terminology">
          <name>Terminology</name>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-nmop-terminology"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Network Telemetry</li>

          <li>Network Analytics</li>

          <li>Value</li>

          <li>State</li>

          <li>Change</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Message Broker</li>

          <li>YANG Message Broker Producer</li>

          <li>YANG Message Broker Consumer</li>

          <li>YANG Schema Registry</li>

          <li>YANG Schema ID</li>

          <li>YANG Data Consumer</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="Kaf11">Apache Kafka</xref> and <xref
        target="Pul16">Apache Pulsar</xref> Message Broker:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Subject: Corresponds to a unique Schema Path within a
          Schema Registry and is used to identify Messages within a
          Topic.</li>

          <li>Topic: A communication channel for publishing and
          subscribing messages with one or more subjects and
          partitions.</li>

          <li>Topic Compaction: The act of compressing messages in a
          topic to the latest state. As used with Apache Pulsar. Apache
          Kafka uses the term Log Compaction with identical meaning.
          </li>

          <li>Partition: Messages in a topic are spread over hash
          buckets where a hash bucket refers to a partition being
          stored within one message broker node. Message ordering is
          guaranteed within a partition.</li>

          <li>Shard: The same as Partition but distributed among
          multiple message broker nodes. In this document, the term
          Partition is being used primarily but the described indexing
          concept equally applies also to Shards.</li>

          <li>Message: A piece of structured data sent between data
          processing components to facilitate communication in a
          distributed system</li>

          <li>Message Key: Metadata associated with a message to
          facilitate deterministic hash bucketing for instantiated
          YANG data.</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="One96">The Log-Structured Merge-Tree</xref> scientific
        paper:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>LSM Tree: Log-Structured Merge-Tree is a data structure
          with performance characteristics that makes it attractive for
          providing indexed access to files with high insert volume. LSM
          trees, like other search trees, maintain key-value pairs.</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="ConDoc18">Confluent Schema Registry
        Documentation</xref>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Schema: A formalized, documented structure that defines
          the shape and content of the messages exchange.</li>

          <li>Schema ID: A unique identifier of a schema associated to a
          Message Broker subject.</li>

          <li>Schema Registry: A system where schemas are registered,
          compared and retrieved.</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="RFC8641"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Periodic Subscription</li>

          <li>On-change Subscription</li>

          <li>Sync-On-Start</li>

          <li>Xpath Filter</li>

          <li>Subtree Filter</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-netconf-notif-envelope"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Notification</li>

          <li>Hostname</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="RFC8342"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Datastore</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="RFC7950"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Schema Node Identifier</li>

          <li>Data Node: Such as "container", "leaf", "leaf-list",
          "list", "choice", "case", "augment", "uses", "anydata", and
          "anyxml" elements.</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in this document:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Schema Path: A specific route to a single, leaf in a
					schema tree. As oposed to a schema tree which represents the
					entire hierarchical structure of a schema, showing how all
					these individual paths branch out and relate to each other as
					a whole.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Solution_Design">
      <name>Solution Design</name>

      <t>To identify which network node produced which YANG data
      instance into which Message Broker Topic, Partition and Subject,
      <xref target="YANG_Message_Keys_Indexes_Solution">YANG
      Message Keys and Indexes</xref> are being introduced. These keys
      enable a deterministic distribution of YANG messages across
      Topics and Partitions enabling applications to consume only the
      needed data from specific topics and partitions.</t>

      <t>In order to facilitate Message Broker Topic Compaction, a
      <xref  target="YANG-Push_Message_Broker_Topic-Naming_Solution">
      YANG-Push subscription type based topic naming scheme</xref> is
      defined. This segregates statistical (Value), State and State
      change YANG metrics and facilitates a YANG Message Broker Consumer
      to use the Topic wild card consumption method to select based on
      YANG-Push subscription type.</t>

      <section anchor="YANG_Message_Keys_Indexes_Solution">
        <name>YANG Message Keys and Indexes</name>

        <t>For topics that carry YANG telemetry messages as defined in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message"/>,
        a Message Key MUST be used. If no Message Key is defined then
        the Messages are distributed in a round robin fashion across
        partitions. If a Message Key is defined, then the value of the
        Message Key is being used as input for the Message Broker
        Producer hash function to distribute across Partitions.
        Therefore, Message Keys facilitate Message deterministic
        distribution.</t>

        <t>The Message Key is not only used for Message indexing at the
        Message Producer but also at the Message Broker for topic
        compaction.</t>

        <t>For YANG, the network node hostname, the YANG-Push
        subscription identifier, and concrete XPath data node
        instances are used to generate the Message Key. The Message
        Key MUST be derived through the three-phase algorithm described
        in <xref target="YANG_Message_Broker_Producer_Key_Solution"/>
        to guarantee deterministic and unambiguous keys.</t>

        <t>The following sections describe the Message Key format,
        the derivation algorithm, and how Message Keys are used in
        both Message producers and Message consumers.</t>

        <section anchor="YANG_Message_Key_Format">
          <name>Message Key Format</name>

          <t>The Message Key is a UTF-8 encoded byte string consisting
          of exactly three fields separated by a single newline
          character (LF, U+000A):</t>

          <ul>
            <li>Line 1: node-name. The managed device identifier,
            typically a hostname or FQDN, as defined in
            "ietf-yang-push-telemetry-message" <xref section="3"
            sectionFormat="of"
            target="I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message"/>.
            </li>

            <li>Line 2: subscription-id. The YANG-Push subscription
            identifier as a decimal string.</li>

            <li>Line 3: One or more concrete XPath expressions,
            sorted lexicographically and deduplicated, joined by
            " | " (space, pipe, space). Each XPath uniquely identifies
            one data node instance within the notification.</li>
          </ul>

          <t>The key MUST NOT contain a trailing newline after the
          XPath line. This ensures byte-identical keys for identical
          inputs, which is the invariant required for Message Broker
          topic compaction.</t>

          <t><xref target="message-key-single-instance-example"/>
          shows a Message Key for a single interface instance on
          node "router-nyc-01" with subscription identifier "1042".
          </t>

<figure anchor="message-key-single-instance-example"
title="Message Key for a Single Interface Instance">
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
router-nyc-01
1042
/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth0']
]]></sourcecode></figure>

          <t><xref target="message-key-multi-instance-example"/>
          shows a Message Key where a single notification carries
          two interface instances. The XPaths are sorted
          lexicographically and joined with " | ".</t>

<figure anchor="message-key-multi-instance-example"
title="Message Key for Multiple Interface Instances">
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
router-nyc-01
1042
/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth0'] | /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth1']
]]></sourcecode></figure>

          <t><xref target="message-key-container-example"/>
          shows a Message Key for a container target (no list
          ancestor). The XPath is the path to the container itself
          with no key predicates.</t>

<figure anchor="message-key-container-example"
title="Message Key for a Container Target">
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
router-nyc-01
1042
/ietf-system:system/clock
]]></sourcecode></figure>

          <t>This line-delimited format guarantees deterministic
          serialization without the ambiguities of structured
          encodings such as JSON (where key ordering and whitespace
          may vary across implementations). The key is a plain byte
          string suitable for direct use as a Message Broker record
          key.</t>

        </section>

        <section anchor="YANG_Message_Broker_Producer_Key_Solution">
          <name>YANG Message Broker Producer</name>

          <t>The Message Key is derived through a three-phase
          algorithm. Phase 1 is only required when the YANG-Push
          subscription uses a subtree filter (<xref section="6"
          sectionFormat="of" target="RFC6241"/>); XPath subscriptions
          skip directly to Phase 2. Phase 2 runs once at subscription
          creation time. Phase 3 runs for every notification.</t>

<figure anchor="algorithm-overview"
title="Three-Phase Message Key Derivation Algorithm">
<artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
+-------------------+       +--------------+
| Subtree Filter    |------>| Phase 1:     |---> Normalized XPath(s)
| (if applicable)   |       | Normalize    |
+-------------------+       +--------------+
                                    |
                                    v
+-------------------+       +--------------+     +---------------+
| Subscription Path |------>|              |     | Key Templates |
| (XPath, possibly  |       |  Phase 2:    |---->| + Extraction  |
|  from Phase 1)    |       |  Schema      |     |   Specs       |
+-------------------+       |  Resolution  |     +---------------+
| YANG Schema Path  |------>|              |
+-------------------+       +--------------+
                                    |
                                    v
+-------------------+       +--------------+     +--------------+
| Parsed Data Path  |------>|              |     | Message Key  |
+-------------------+       |  Phase 3:    |---->| (line-       |
| Node Name         |------>|  Data Walk   |     |  delimited)  |
| Subscription ID   |------>|              |     |              |
+-------------------+       +--------------+     +--------------+
]]></artwork></figure>

          <section anchor="Phase1">
            <name>Phase 1: Subtree Filter Normalization</name>

            <t><xref section="3.6" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC8641"/>
            defines how YANG data nodes can be subscribed with subtree
            and xpath selection filters. When a subtree filter is used,
            the XML representation MUST first be normalized into one or
            more equivalent XPath expressions before proceeding to
            Phase 2.</t>

            <t>The normalization follows the element classification
            defined in <xref section="6.2" sectionFormat="of"
            target="RFC6241"/>. Each child element in the subtree
            filter is classified based on its content:</t>

            <ul>
              <li>Content match node: The element has text content
              and no child elements. It becomes an XPath predicate
              of the form [module:key='value'] on the parent path
              step.</li>

              <li>Selection node: The element has no text content and
              no child elements. It becomes a terminal XPath branch.
              </li>

              <li>Containment node: The element has child elements
              (with no text content or only whitespace). It becomes
              an intermediate path step and the algorithm recurses
              into its children.</li>
            </ul>

            <t>An element whose text content consists only of
            whitespace (spaces, tabs, newlines) MUST NOT be treated
            as a content match. It is classified as a selection or
            containment node depending on whether it has children.</t>

            <t>Each path segment in the output carries the YANG
            module-name prefix. Duplicate XPath branches MUST be
            deduplicated. Multiple branches are joined with " | ".
            </t>

            <t>For example, the subtree filter shown in <xref
            target="phase1-subtree-example"/> normalizes to the
            XPath expression shown in <xref
            target="phase1-xpath-result"/>.</t>

<figure anchor="phase1-subtree-example"
title="Subtree Filter Example">
<sourcecode type="xml"><![CDATA[
<interfaces xmlns=
    "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-interfaces">
  <interface>
    <name>eth0</name>
    <oper-status/>
  </interface>
</interfaces>
]]></sourcecode></figure>

<figure anchor="phase1-xpath-result"
title="Normalized XPath from Subtree Filter">
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/ietf-interfaces:interface
    [ietf-interfaces:name='eth0']
    /ietf-interfaces:oper-status
]]></sourcecode></figure>

            <t>In this example the "name" element is classified
            as a content match (it has text content "eth0"), producing
            the predicate [ietf-interfaces:name='eth0'] on the
            "interface" path step. The "oper-status" element is
            classified as a selection node, becoming the terminal
            branch.</t>

          </section>

          <section anchor="Phase2">
            <name>Phase 2: Key Template Derivation</name>

            <t>Given a subscription XPath (from Phase 1 or directly
            from an XPath subscription) and a compiled YANG schema
            context, Phase 2 resolves each union branch to its target
            schema node, walks the ancestor chain from root to target,
            and builds a key template.</t>

            <t>The subscription XPath is first split on top-level "|"
            into individual branches (respecting brackets, quotes,
            and parentheses). Each branch is processed independently.
            </t>

            <t>For each branch, the algorithm resolves the XPath to
            its target schema node using the YANG Schema Path. It
            then walks the ancestor chain from the schema root to the
            target node, building the key template path. For each
            node in the path:</t>

            <ul>
              <li>The path segment uses minimal-prefix style: the
              YANG module name appears only on the first segment or
              when the module changes from the previous segment.</li>

              <li>If the node is a YANG list (<xref section="7.8"
              sectionFormat="of" target="RFC7950"/>), key predicates
              are appended for each schema-defined key leaf in schema
              order. If the subscription XPath contains a matching
              predicate with a literal value, that value is embedded
              in the template (pinned key). Otherwise, a placeholder
              marker is used indicating that the value must be
              extracted from the notification data at runtime (open
              key).</li>

              <li>If the target node is a YANG leaf-list, a value
              predicate [.='...'] is appended, either as a pinned
              literal or as an open placeholder.</li>

              <li>YANG choice and case nodes are skipped as they are
              not data nodes.</li>
            </ul>

            <t>The following predicate normalizations are applied
            during template derivation:</t>

            <ul>
              <li>No predicate in subscription: open placeholder +
              extraction spec.</li>

              <li>[key='value']: literal value embedded as-is
              (pinned).</li>

              <li>[module:key='value']: module prefix stripped,
              literal value embedded.</li>

              <li>[key="value"]: double-quote normalized to
              single-quote.</li>

              <li>[N] (positional predicate): treated as open
              (positional subscripts do not identify a specific
              instance by key).</li>
            </ul>

            <t><xref target="phase2-template-example"/> shows the
            key template derived from the XPath subscription
            "/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface". Because the
            "interface" list has a key leaf "name" and the
            subscription does not pin it, the template contains an
            open placeholder for the "name" key.</t>

<figure anchor="phase2-template-example"
title="Key Template for an Open Interface Subscription">
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
Template:    /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='%s']
Extraction:  /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface/name
]]></sourcecode></figure>

            <t><xref target="phase2-pinned-example"/> shows the
            key template when the subscription pins the outer list
            key but leaves the inner list open:
            "/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth0']
            /ietf-ip:ipv4/address".</t>

<figure anchor="phase2-pinned-example"
title="Key Template with Pinned Outer Key and Open Inner Key">
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
Template:    /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/ietf-ip:ipv4/address[ip='%s']
Extraction:  /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/ietf-ip:ipv4/address/ip
]]></sourcecode></figure>

            <t>Phase 2 produces one key template per union branch,
            together with extraction specifications that describe
            which key leaf values must be extracted from the data
            tree at runtime to fill each open placeholder. Each
            extraction is expressed as an absolute XPath that
            identifies the key leaf in the data tree. The path
            mirrors the template path from the root to the owning
            list (preserving any pinned predicates on ancestor lists)
            and appends the key leaf name without a predicate:</t>

            <t>/MODULE:CONTAINER/.../LIST/KEY-LEAF-NAME</t>

            <t>When evaluated against a notification data tree, this
            XPath selects the key leaf value(s) of the matching list
            instance(s). For leaf-list targets, the extraction is
            simply "." (the data node's own value).</t>

          </section>

          <section anchor="Phase3">
            <name>Phase 3: Runtime Key Production</name>

            <t>For each notification, the parsed data tree is walked
            and matched against the branch templates from Phase 2.
            For each matching data node instance:</t>

            <ol>
              <li>The open placeholders in the key template are filled
              with the actual key leaf values from the data tree by
              evaluating the extraction XPath from Phase 2. Each
              extraction XPath selects the key leaf value(s) of the
              matching list instance(s) in the notification data.</li>

              <li>For leaf-list targets, the data node's own value
              fills the [.='%s'] placeholder.</li>
            </ol>

            <t>As an optimization, implementations need not invoke a
            full XPath evaluator for each extraction. Because the
            extraction path always leads to a key leaf of an ancestor
            list, it can be rewritten to an equivalent
            "ancestor-or-self" axis expression evaluated relative to
            the matched data node. For example, the extraction
            "/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface/name" becomes
            "ancestor-or-self::ietf-interfaces:interface/name". This
            reduces evaluation to a simple upward tree walk from the
            matched data node to the first ancestor whose schema node
            matches the list name, followed by reading a direct child.
            This yields O(d) complexity where d is the depth of the
            data tree, which is typically small (3 to 8 levels for
            common YANG models).</t>

            <t>All filled XPath expressions (concrete XPaths) are
            collected, deduplicated, and sorted lexicographically.
            The final Message Key is then composed as defined in
            <xref target="YANG_Message_Key_Format"/>: the node-name
            and subscription-id on separate lines, followed by the
            concrete XPaths joined by " | " on a third line.</t>

            <t><xref target="phase3-example"/> shows the complete
            derivation for a notification carrying two interface
            instances.</t>

<figure anchor="phase3-example"
title="End-to-End Example: Subscription to Key">
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
Subscription XPath:
  /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface

Phase 2 Template:
  /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='%s']

Notification data (XML):
  <interfaces xmlns=
      "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-interfaces">
    <interface>
      <name>eth0</name>
      <oper-status>up</oper-status>
    </interface>
    <interface>
      <name>eth1</name>
      <oper-status>down</oper-status>
    </interface>
  </interfaces>

Concrete XPaths (sorted):
  /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth0']
  /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth1']

Message Key:
  router-nyc-01
  1042
  /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth0'] | /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth1']
]]></sourcecode></figure>

            <t>When the subscription targets a YANG container (with
            no list ancestor), there are no open placeholders and no
            instances to match. In that case, the key template itself
            is used as the single concrete XPath in the Message
            Key.</t>

          </section>

          <section anchor="Subtree_Filter_End_to_End">
            <name>Subtree Filter End-to-End Example</name>

            <t><xref target="subtree-e2e-example"/> illustrates the
            complete three-phase derivation starting from a subtree
            filter subscription that spans two YANG modules. The
            filter selects the "oper-status" leaf of interface "eth0"
            from "ietf-interfaces" <xref target="RFC8343"/> (concrete
            branch, key pinned in the filter) and the "serial-num"
            leaf of every hardware component from "ietf-hardware"
            <xref target="RFC8348"/> (non-concrete branch, no key
            value in the filter). Phase 1 produces a union of two
            branches. Phase 2 derives one fully-concrete template
            (key pinned) and one template with an open placeholder
            for the component "name" key. Phase 3 evaluates the
            open placeholder against the notification data, expanding
            the single template into one concrete XPath per matching
            component instance.</t>

<figure anchor="subtree-e2e-example"
title="End-to-End Example Starting from Subtree Filter">
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
Subtree filter:
  <interfaces xmlns=
      "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-interfaces">
    <interface>
      <name>eth0</name>
      <oper-status/>
    </interface>
  </interfaces>
  <hardware xmlns=
      "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-hardware">
    <component>
      <serial-num/>
    </component>
  </hardware>

Phase 1 (Normalize):
  /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/ietf-interfaces:interface[ietf-interfaces:name='eth0']/ietf-interfaces:oper-status
  | /ietf-hardware:hardware/ietf-hardware:component/ietf-hardware:serial-num

Phase 2 (Two branch templates):
  Branch 0 (leaf target, key pinned):
    /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/oper-status
    (fully concrete)

  Branch 1 (leaf target, key open):
    /ietf-hardware:hardware/component[name='%s']/serial-num
    Extraction:
      /ietf-hardware:hardware/component/name
    (open placeholder: name)

Notification data (XML):
  <interfaces xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-interfaces">
    <interface>
      <name>eth0</name>
      <oper-status>up</oper-status>
    </interface>
  </interfaces>
  <hardware xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-hardware">
    <component>
      <name>chassis</name>
      <serial-num>SN-12345</serial-num>
    </component>
    <component>
      <name>fan-1</name>
      <serial-num>SN-67890</serial-num>
    </component>
  </hardware>

Phase 3 (Key production):

Concrete XPaths (sorted):
  /ietf-hardware:hardware/component[name='chassis']/serial-num
  /ietf-hardware:hardware/component[name='fan-1']/serial-num
  /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/oper-status

Message Key:
  router-nyc-01
  1042
  /ietf-hardware:hardware/component[name='chassis']/serial-num | /ietf-hardware:hardware/component[name='fan-1']/serial-num | /ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/oper-status
]]></sourcecode></figure>

            <t>When the Message is being produced to the Message Broker,
            the network node hostname is used from the structured YANG
            data defined in "ietf-yang-push-telemetry-message" <xref
            section="3" sectionFormat="of"
            target="I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message"/>.
            The concrete XPath expressions are derived from the
            subscription filter and the YANG Schema Path as described
            above, and then instantiated with values from each
            notification data path.</t>

          </section>

        </section>

        <section anchor="YANG_Message_Broker_Consumer_Key_Solution">
          <name>YANG Message Broker Consumer</name>

          <t>The consumer hashes the Message Key, applies modulo with
          the number of partitions, and determines the partition from
          which it should consume messages bearing that Message Key.</t>

          <t>To parse the Message Key, the consumer splits the byte
          string on newline (LF) characters. The first line is the
          node-name, the second is the subscription-id, and the
          third line contains the concrete XPath expression(s)
          joined by " | ".</t>

          <t>At a YANG data store, such as a Time Series database or
          stream processor, the YANG data could then be ingested into
          tables according to topic names and indexed per Message Key.
          If Topic Compaction is enabled, only current state is
          consumed.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Time_Series_Database">
          <name>Time Series Database</name>
          <t>Depending if the YANG Data Consumer knows the Message Key
          from the YANG Message Broker Consumer or the YANG Schema from
          the YANG Schema Registry the network telemetry messages can be
          indexed in a Time series database. The Message Key could serve
          as the primary key, while the individual fields (node-name,
          subscription-id, concrete XPaths) can be reflected in the
          indexing scheme using primary and secondary keys in a time
          series database. Implementation examples can be found under
          <xref target="TSDB_Implementations"/>.</t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section anchor="YANG-Push_Message_Broker_Topic-Naming_Solution">
        <name>YANG-Push Message Broker Topic Naming</name>

        <t>Each YANG-Push subscription requires a deterministic,
        human-readable Message Broker topic name. The topic name MUST
        satisfy the following requirements:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Deterministic: The same subscription, regardless of
          syntactic form (XPath vs. subtree filter, redundant module
          prefixes, single-quoted vs. double-quoted predicates), MUST
          always produce the same topic name.</li>

          <li>Unique: Two subscriptions targeting different YANG schema
          nodes MUST NOT share a topic name.</li>

          <li>Human-readable: An operator inspecting a topic listing
          SHOULD be able to identify which YANG data the topic
          carries.</li>

          <li>Stable under schema evolution: Augmenting the YANG schema
          with new nodes MUST NOT change existing topic names. Any
          optimization that depends on the current set of schema
          siblings (e.g. dropping zero-entropy wrapper containers or
          using shortest-unique-prefix abbreviation) is therefore
          unsafe and MUST NOT be used.</li>

          <li>Within Message Broker limits: Topic names MUST contain
          only characters permitted by the Message Broker (for Apache
          Kafka: [a-zA-Z0-9._-], maximum 249 characters).</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The topic name is derived from the Phase 2 key template
        (see <xref target="Phase2"/>) through a purely mechanical
        transformation of the YANG schema DATA path. No additional
        schema resolution is needed beyond Phase 2.</t>

        <section anchor="Topic_Naming_Algorithm">
          <name>Topic Name Derivation Algorithm</name>

          <t>The input is the Phase 2 key template for one branch
          of the subscription. For union subscriptions with multiple
          branches, each branch produces its own topic name
          independently.</t>

          <t>The derivation proceeds in five steps:</t>

          <ol>
            <li>Strip Predicates: Remove all predicate expressions
            ([...]) from the key template. This yields the schema
            DATA path, the structural identity of the subscription
            target, independent of any specific instance.
            For example,
            "/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface[name='%s']"
            becomes "/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface".</li>

            <li>Replace Module Names with YANG Prefixes: Walk the
            path segments. Wherever a segment carries a
            "module-name:local-name" prefix, look up the module in
            the YANG schema context and substitute its <xref
            section="6.5" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC7950">prefix
            statement</xref>. YANG module prefixes are short by
            convention (2-6 characters), unique within any loaded
            schema context, and immutable once a module is published
            (<xref section="4.1" sectionFormat="of"
            target="RFC7950"/>).
            For example,
            "/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface" becomes
            "/if:interfaces/interface".</li>

            <li>Flatten to Topic Name: Apply three mechanical
            substitutions: (a) remove the leading "/", (b) replace
            every ":" with "-", (c) replace every "/" with "-".
            For example, "if:interfaces/interface" becomes
            "if-interfaces-interface". All resulting characters
            ([a-z0-9-]) are valid in Message Broker topic names.</li>

            <li>Prepend Organization Prefix (Optional): When an
            organization, team, or project prefix is configured, it
            is prepended with a "-" separator.
            For example, "if-interfaces-interface" becomes
            "netops-if-interfaces-interface".
            The prefix MUST contain only Message Broker safe
            characters. When no prefix is configured, this step is
            a no-op.</li>

            <li>Handle Overflow: If the resulting name exceeds the
            maximum topic name length (configurable, default 255),
            it is truncated at the last "-" boundary that keeps the
            name within the budget, and an 8-character hexadecimal
            hash suffix (FNV-1a 64-bit of the full Schema Path) is
            appended for uniqueness. In practice, overflow rarely
            triggers — the longest realistic YANG paths produce topic
            names of 50-80 characters.</li>
          </ol>

          <t><xref target="topic-name-derivation-example"/> shows
          the derivation for three subscription paths.</t>

<figure anchor="topic-name-derivation-example"
title="Topic Name Derivation Examples">
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
Subscription XPath                                 Topic Name
------------------------------------------------------  -------------------
/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface              if-interfaces-interface
/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface/oper-status  if-interfaces-interface-oper-status
/ietf-system:system/clock                          sys-system-clock
/ietf-system:system/dns-resolver/server            sys-system-dns-resolver-server
]]></sourcecode></figure>

          <t><xref target="topic-name-prefix-example"/> shows the
          same paths with an organization prefix "netops".</t>

<figure anchor="topic-name-prefix-example"
title="Topic Names with Organization Prefix">
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
Subscription XPath                                 Topic Name
------------------------------------------------------  -------------------
/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface              netops-if-interfaces-interface
/ietf-interfaces:interfaces/interface/oper-status  netops-if-interfaces-interface-oper-status
/ietf-system:system/clock                          netops-sys-system-clock
]]></sourcecode></figure>

        </section>

        <section anchor="Topic_Naming_Properties">
          <name>Properties</name>

          <t>The topic naming algorithm has the following properties:
          </t>

          <ul>
            <li>The mapping is injective (one-to-one): given a topic
            name, the original Schema Path can be reconstructed by
            reversing the substitutions. Different Schema Paths always
            produce different topic names.</li>

            <li>The topic name depends only on the subscription's own
            path segments and their YANG module prefixes. It does not
            depend on what other nodes exist at the same schema level.
            Augmenting the schema adds new topic names but never
            changes existing ones.</li>

            <li>The "-" separator creates a natural hierarchy for
            pattern matching. For example, "^if-interfaces-interface-.*"
            matches all interface leaf topics, and "^if-.*" matches
            all topics from the ietf-interfaces module.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>

        <section anchor="YANG_Message_Broker_Producer_Topic_Solution">
          <name>YANG Message Broker Producer</name>

          <t>The YANG Message Broker Producer derives the topic name
          from the YANG-Push subscription's xpath or subtree filter
          by running Phases 1 and 2 (as described in <xref
          target="YANG_Message_Broker_Producer_Key_Solution"/>) and
          then applying the topic name derivation algorithm above.
          The subscription type ("periodic", "on-change", or
          "on-change" with "sync-on-start") MAY be encoded in a separate
					topic hierarchy level, depending on the deployment's naming
					policy. Where "periodic" is encoded as "stats", "on-change" as
					"state-change", "on-change" with "sync-on-start" as "state"
					and "on-change" with "sync-on-start" whre topic compaction
					is enabled as "current-state".</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="YANG_Message_Broker_Consumer_Topic_Solution">
          <name>YANG Message Broker Consumer</name>

          <t>The consumer can subscribe to multiple topics using
          wildcard or regex patterns. For example:</t>

          <ul>
            <li>All interface data: "^if-interfaces-interface.*"</li>

            <li>All data from a specific module:
            "^if-.*" (ietf-interfaces) or
            "^sys-.*" (ietf-system)</li>

            <li>All data from an organization:
            "^netops-.*"</li>

            <li>All current-state data from an organization:
            "^netops-current-state-.*"</li>
          </ul>

          <t>The YANG data is then ingested into tables according to
          topic names and indexed per Message Key. If Topic Compaction
          is enabled, only the current state is consumed.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Message_Broker_Implementations">
      <name>Message Broker Implementations</name>

      <t>Topic, Partitioning and Message Keys are generic concepts of
      Message Brokers. There are two known Message Broker
      implementations supporting all features described in this
      document.</t>

      <section anchor="MB_Implementations_Kafka">
        <name>Apache Kafka</name>

        <t>Apache Kafka supports Message Keys, Partitioning and Log
        Compaction.</t>

        <t>With the following example from the Apache Kafka admin client
        API <eref target="https://kafka.apache.org/41/javadoc/org/apache/kafka/clients/admin/Admin.html"/>
        a new compacted Topic can be created.</t>

<artwork><![CDATA[
Properties props = new Properties();
props.put(AdminClientConfig.BOOTSTRAP_SERVERS_CONFIG, "localhost:9092");

try (Admin admin = Admin.create(props)) {
 String topicName = "my-topic";
 int partitions = 12;
 short replicationFactor = 3;
 // Create a compacted topic
 CreateTopicsResult result = admin.createTopics(Collections.singleton(
  new NewTopic(topicName, partitions, replicationFactor)
   .configs(Collections.singletonMap(TopicConfig.CLEANUP_POLICY_CONFIG,/
   TopicConfig.CLEANUP_POLICY_COMPACT))));

 // Call values() to get the result for a specific topic
 // KafkaFuture<Void> future = result.values().get(topicName);

 // Call get() to block until the topic creation is complete or has
 // failed if creation failed the ExecutionException wraps the
 // underlying cause. future.get();
}
]]></artwork>

        <t>The most important configuration items from
        <eref target="https://kafka.apache.org/41/configuration/topic-configs/"/>
        are "topicName" defines the Topic name, "partitions" the amount
        of partitions, "replicationFactor" how many times the partition
        is being replicated.</t>

        <t>With "compact" in "cleanup.policy" the log compaction can be
        turned on per topic. With "min.cleanable.dirty.ratio" and
        "delete.retention.ms" how often and when Log Compaction should
        occur per topic. Where with "retention.bytes" and with
        "retention.ms" the topic specific compaction configurations can
        be limited how often the topics are compacted.</t>

        <t>The topic names are constrained to 249 character
        length and the following characters: "a-z", "A-Z", "0-9", ".",
        "_" and "-". Topics can be created on the fly by producing into
        a new Topic when "auto.create.topics.enable" has been configured
        prior. Topics should be deleted at the end of the lifecycle
        through the "kafka-topics.sh" command.</t>

        <t>The Partition count for a given Topic can be increased but
        not decreased. Consumer groups are automatically re-joined and
        partitions are being rebalanced on Message Broker nodes when
        Partition count changed.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="MB_Implementations_Pulsar">
        <name>Apache Pulsar</name>

        <t>Apache Pulsar supports Message Keys, Partitioning and Topic
        Compaction.</t>

        <t>With "brokerServiceCompactionThreshold" when Topic Compaction
        should occur is being configured.</t>

        <t>The topic names allow all characters except: "/".
        Topics can be created on the fly by producing into a new Topic
        when "allowAutoTopicCreation" has been configured prior. Topics
        should be deleted at the end of the lifecycle through
        pulsar-admin or pulsarctl tools.</t>

        <t>The Partition count for a given Topic can be increased but
        not decreased. Consumer groups are automatically re-joined and
        partitions are being rebalanced on Message Broker nodes when
        Partition count changed.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="TSDB_Implementations">
      <name>Time Series Database Implementations</name>

      <t>Tables, partition and keys are generic concepts of time series
      databases. With ClickHouse, this document provides examples of
      how YANG message keys can be obtained from the Message Broker and
      used for indexing.</t>

      <section anchor="TSDB_Implementations_ClickHouse">
        <name>ClickHouse</name>

        <section anchor="ClickHouse_Data_Model">
          <name>Data Model</name>

          <t>Unlike other realtime analytics databases, ClickHouse does
          not (necessarily) rely on partitioning data by timestamp.
          ClickHouse represents data in the MergeTree format, which is
          similar to a LSM tree:</t>

          <t>A table consists of data parts sorted by primary key.</t>

          <t>When data is inserted in a table, separate data parts are
          created  and each of data part is lexicographically sorted by
          primary key. For example, if the primary key is ("MessageKey",
          "Date"), the data in the part is sorted by "MessageKey", and
          within each "MessageKey", it is ordered by "Date".</t>

          <t>Data belonging to different partitions are separated into
          different parts. In the background, ClickHouse merges data
          parts for more efficient storage. Parts belonging to different
          partitions are not merged. The merge mechanism does not
          guarantee that all rows with the same primary key will be in
          the same data part.</t>

          <t>Each data part is logically divided into granules. A granule
          is the smallest indivisible data set that ClickHouse reads
          when selecting data. ClickHouse does not split rows or values,
          so each granule always contains an integer number of rows. The
          first row of a granule is marked with the value of the primary
          key for the row. For each data part, ClickHouse creates an
          index file that stores the marks. For each column, whether
          it's in the primary key or not, ClickHouse also stores the
          same marks. These marks let you find data directly in column
          files.</t>

          <t>Thus, it is possible to quickly run queries on one or many
          ranges of the primary key.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ClickHouse_Message_Broker_Integration">
          <name>Message Broker Integration</name>

          <t>ClickHouse integrates with Message Brokers through
          Integration Table Engines.</t>

          <t>Reading (selecting) data through Kafka Table Engine follows
          Apache Kafka semantics of advancing the offset, so subsequent
          reads will start at the offset the previous read left off.</t>

          <t>It is the responsibility of the data model designer to
          transfer data to a regular table:</t>

          <ul>
            <li>Use the engine to create a Kafka consumer and consider
            it a data stream.</li>
          </ul>

          <t>Example:</t>

          <artwork><![CDATA[
          CREATE TABLE queue (
              timestamp UInt64,
              level String,
              message String
          )
          ENGINE = Kafka
          SETTINGS kafka_broker_list = 'localhost:9092',
              kafka_topic_list = 'topic',
              kafka_group_name = 'group1',
              kafka_format = 'JSONEachRow',
              kafka_num_consumers = 4;
          ]]></artwork>

          <ul>
            <li>Create a table with the desired structure.</li>
          </ul>

          <t>Example:</t>

          <artwork><![CDATA[
          CREATE TABLE messages (
              key String,
              timestamp UInt64,
              level String,
              message String
          )
          ENGINE = MergeTree
          ORDER BY (key, timestamp);
          ]]></artwork>

          <ul>
            <li>Create a materialized view that converts data from the
            engine and puts it into a previously created table.</li>
          </ul>

          <artwork><![CDATA[
          CREATE MATERIALIZED VIEW mv_messages TO messages AS
          SELECT
              _key AS key,
              timestamp,
              level,
              message
          FROM queue;
          ]]></artwork>

          <t>The Message Key and partition ID are available as virtual
          (read only) columns _key and _partition.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ClickHouse_Message_Formats">
          <name>Message Formats</name>

          <t>ClickHouse supports numerous Message formats natively. The
          example above uses the JSON Lines format but other (binary)
          formats, such as Apache Avro or Protobuf, are supported as
          well.</t>

        </section>

        <section anchor="ClickHouse_Schema_Registry">
          <name>Schema Registry</name>

          <t>ClickHouse has built in Schema Registry support. For Apache
          Avro, the Schema Registry and authentication are encoded in
          additional parameters to the Apache Kafka consumer.</t>

          <t>For formats such as Confluent JSON_SR, use the
          "kafka_schema_registry_skip_bytes" parameter to skip reading
          the Schema Registry preamble. The Schema can then be encoded
          explicitly.</t>

        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document should not affect the security of the Internet.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Operational">
      <name>Operational Considerations</name>
      <t>The YANG Message Broker Producer of a YANG-Push receiver should
      have three config knobs facilitate the features described in this
      document as optional:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Topic Distribution: Select between "topic" and "subject"
          distribution. Default is subject to remain backward
          compatibility to <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration"/>.</li>

          <li>Distribution Type: Select between "none" and
          "YANG-Push subscription type".</li>

          <li>YANG Message Key: Select between "enable" and "disable".
          </li>
        </ul>

      <t>Subject distribution enables message ordering for a set of
      YANG Message Keys on each partition. Where in topic distribution
      messages are randomly being distributed among partitions.</t>

      <t>To accommodate for potential date loss throughout the data
      processing pipeline, periodic
      update of the current State for
      State metrics is RECOMMENDED. This can be accommodated with
      YANG-Push as defined in <xref target="RFC8641"/> by complementing
      "on-change sync on start" subscriptions with "periodic"
      subscriptions. Alternatively, in YANG-Push Lite defined in
      <xref section="7.6" sectionFormat="of"
      target="I-D.wilton-netconf-yang-push-lite"/> this simplified in
      one subscription.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6241.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7950.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8342.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8641.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netconf-notif-envelope.xml"/>
      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8340.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8343.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8348.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-nmop-terminology.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.wilton-netconf-yang-push-lite.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="Mar24"
                   target="https://arxiv.org/html/2402.06511v1">
          <front>
            <title>Toward Building a Semantic Network Inventory for Model-Driven Telemetry</title>

            <author fullname="Ignacio D. Martinez-Casanueva" surname="D. Martinez-Casanueva"/>
            <author fullname="Daniel Gonzalez-Sanchez" surname="Gonzalez-Sanchez"/>
            <author fullname="Luis Bellido" surname="Bellido"/>
            <author fullname="David Fernandez" surname="Fernandez"/>
            <author fullname="Diego R. Lopez" surname="Lopez"/>

            <date month="February" year="2024"/>
          </front>

          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/MCOM.001.2200222"/>

          <refcontent>IEEE</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Bod24"
                   target="https://arxiv.org/html/2302.01713v4">
          <front>
            <title>Toward Avoiding the Data Mess: Industry Insights From Data Mesh Implementations</title>

            <author fullname="Jan Bode" surname="Bode"/>
            <author fullname="Niklas Kühl" surname="Kühl"/>
            <author fullname="Dominik Kreuzberger" surname="Kreuzberger"/>
            <author fullname="Carsten Holtmann" surname="Holtmann"/>

            <date month="January" year="2024"/>
          </front>

          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/ACCESS.2024.3417291"/>

          <refcontent>IEEE</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Deh22"
                   target="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/data-mesh/9781492092384/">
          <front>
            <title>Data Mesh</title>

            <author fullname="Zhamak Dehghani" initials="Z." surname="Dehghani"/>

            <date month="March" year="2022"/>
          </front>

          <seriesInfo name="ISBN" value="9781492092391"/>

          <refcontent>O'Reilly Media</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Kim96"
                   target="https://www.kimballgroup.com/data-warehouse-business-intelligence-resources/books/data-warehouse-dw-toolkit/">
          <front>
            <title>The Data Warehouse Toolkit</title>

            <author fullname="Ralph Kimball" surname="Kimball"/>
            <author fullname="Margy Ross" surname="Ross"/>

            <date year="1996"/>
          </front>

          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1007/s002360050048"/>

          <refcontent>Wiley</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="One96"
                   target="https://www.cs.umb.edu/~poneil/lsmtree.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>The Log-Structured Merge-Tree</title>

            <author fullname="Patrick O'Neil" surname="O'Neil"/>
            <author fullname="Edward Cheng" surname="Cheng"/>
            <author fullname="Dieter Gawlick" surname="Gawlick"/>
            <author fullname="Elizabeth O'Neil" surname="O'Neil"/>

            <date year="1996"/>
          </front>

          <seriesInfo name="ISBN" value="9781118530801"/>

          <refcontent>Acta Informatica</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Kaf11" target="https://kafka.apache.org/">
          <front>
            <title>Apache Kafka</title>

            <author fullname="Neha Narkhede" initials="N." surname="Narkhede"/>

            <date month="January" year="2011"/>
          </front>

          <refcontent>Apache Software Foundation</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Pul16" target="https://pulsar.apache.org/">
          <front>
            <title>Apache Pulsar</title>

            <author fullname="Sijie Guo" initials="S." surname="Guo"/>

            <author fullname="Matteo  Merli" initials="M." surname="Merli"/>

            <date month="January" year="2016"/>
          </front>

          <refcontent>Apache Software Foundation</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="ConDoc18"
                   target="https://docs.confluent.io/platform/current/schema-registry/">
          <front>
            <title>Confluent Schema Registry Documentation</title>

            <author fullname="Robert Yokota " initials="R." surname="Yokota"/>

            <date month="December" year="2018"/>
          </front>

          <refcontent>Confluent Community and Apache Software
          Foundation</refcontent>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Thanks to Camilo Cardona, Rob Wilton, Holger Keller, Reshad
      Rahman, Nigel Davis, Olga Havel and Michael Mackey for their
      comments and reviews.</t>

      <t>We also like to thank Victor Lopez for the initial idea on the
      network controller use case. Ashley Woods, Sivakumar
      Sundaravadivel and Rafael Julio for the idea of grouping topics by
      YANG-Push subscription type and insisting that Topic Compaction
      is a key enabler for inventory metrics and YANG data consumer
      integration and should be supported day 1. Nigel Davis for
      confirming that Topic Compaction simplifies indeed data processing
      system architecture and Loic Monney for the operational
      configuration and monitoring details on Apache Kafka.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Contributors" numbered="false">
      <name>Contributors</name>

      <t>Many thanks goes to Hellmar Becker who contributed <xref
      target="Time_Series_Database"/> and <xref
      target="TSDB_Implementations"/> on how YANG Message Keys can be
      obtained from Message Broker, how time series databases can use
      it for indexing YANG data and example implementation in
      ClickHouse.</t>

      <author fullname="Hellmar Becker" initials="HB" surname="Becker">

        <organization>ClickHouse</organization>
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>601 Marshall Street</street>
            <city>Redwood City</city>
            <code>CA 94063</code>
            <country>US</country>
          </postal>
          <email>hellmar.becker@clickhouse.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>
    </section>

 </back>
</rfc>
