<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- If further character entities are required then they should be added to the DOCTYPE above.
     Use of an external entity file is not recommended. -->

<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="std"
  docName="draft-netana-nmop-yang-message-broker-message-key-01"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates=""
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="YANG Message Keys"> YANG Message Keys for
     Message Broker Integration</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-netana-nmop-yang-message-broker-message-key-01"/>
   
    <author fullname="Thomas Graf" initials="TG" surname="Graf">

      <organization>Swisscom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Binzring 17</street>
          <city>Zurich</city>
          <code>8045</code>
          <country>CH</country>
        </postal>        
        <email>thomas.graf@swisscom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ahmed Elhassany" initials="AE" surname="Elhassany">

      <organization>Swisscom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Binzring 17</street>
          <city>Zurich</city>
          <code>8045</code>
          <country>CH</country>
        </postal>        
        <email>ahmed.elhassany@swisscom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Alex Huang Feng" initials="AHF" surname="Huang Feng">

      <organization>INSA-Lyon</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Lyon</city>
          <country>FR</country>
        </postal>        
        <email>alex.huang-feng@insa-lyon.fr</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Benoît Claise" initials="BC" surname="Claise">

    <organization>Everything OPS</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Liege</city>
          <country>BE</country>
        </postal>        
        <email>benoit@everything-ops.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
   
    <date day="20" month="October" year="2025"/>

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>NMOP</workgroup>
    <keyword>YANG-Push</keyword>
    <keyword>Data Mesh</keyword>
    <keyword>Network Telemetry</keyword>
    <keyword>Network Analytics</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies a mechanism to define a unique message
      key for a YANG to message broker integration and a topic
      addressing scheme based on YANG-Push subscription type and a YANG
      index defined in this document. This enables YANG data consumption
			of a subset of subscribed YANG data, either per specific YANG
			node, identifier or telemetry message type, by indexing and
			organizing in Message Broker topics, indexing the information the
			right way.</t>
    </abstract>
 
  </front>

  <middle>
    
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>Nowadays network operators are using machine and human
      readable <xref target="RFC7950">YANG</xref> to model their
      configurations and monitor YANG operational data from
      their networks according to <xref target="Mar24"/>.</t>

      <t>Most network analytic use cases require real-time data and
      deliver near real-time analytical, actionable insights. This
      imposes high scalability, resilience and low overhead in the data
      processing pipeline. Accessing the right data for the right use
      case with minimal overhead and in the shortest period of time is
      therefore crucial.</t> 
    
      <t>Network operators organize their data in a <xref
      target="Deh22">Data Mesh</xref> according to <xref
      target="Bod24"/> where a Message Broker such as <xref
      target="Kaf11">Apache Kafka</xref> or <xref target="Pul16">Apache
      Pulsar</xref> facilitates the exchange of messages among data
      processing components in topics and subjects. Typically, data is
      being stored in Message Broker topics for several hours or days
      to facilitate resilience in the data processing chain and
      addressed in subjects depending on schema, enabling a data
      consumer to address and re-consume previously consumed data again
      if previously lost.</t>

      <t>Dimensional data is structured information in a data store.
      It uses a model of dimension tables to organize business metrics
      and their descriptive context. This model, developed by <xref
      target="Kim96">Ralph Kimball</xref>, simplifies data analysis and
      reporting by creating denormalized, easy-to-understand structures
      for quick querying. It is optimized for online analytical
      processing (OLAP) and data warehouses. <xref
      target="RFC7950">YANG</xref> as a data modelling language
      facilitates the modelling of dimensional data.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration">An
      Architecture for YANG-Push to Message Broker Integration</xref>
      specifies an architecture for integrating YANG-Push with
      Message Brokers for a Data Mesh architecture. How the 
      notification messages at a YANG-Push Receiver are being transformed
      to the Message Broker is described in <xref
      section="4.5" sectionFormat="of"
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration"/> and
      to which message schema in <xref section="3" sectionFormat="of"
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message"/>, however 
      how messages should be indexed best for dimensional YANG data is
      left unspecified.</t>

      <t>Due to the missing dimensional indexing for Message Broker
      stored YANG data, all YANG data is stored in one single Topic,
      distributed round robin across multiple Partitions and each YANG
      schema id is a subject within that topic. Therefore, the entire
      Topic from all Partitions needs to be consumed first before data
      selection can be applied. This leads to avoidable data processing
      overhead which in turn impairs scalability and real-time
      capabilities, required for certain Network Analytics
      use cases.</t>

      <t>YANG telmetry data can be used for several network analytic use
			cases. Importantly, depending on the use case, only a subset of
			the subscribed YANG data might be necessary (in time or space).
			For example, for specific use cases, it's more important to know 
      the current network state, as opposed to have the full series of
			the state changes over time. In other use cases, instead of
			consuming data for all network nodes, only a specific network node
			or network node component requires the YANG monitoring and hence
			subscription.</t>
       
      <t>This document defines how YANG messages <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message"/> should
			be indexed and organized in Message Broker topics by leveraging
			the network node hostname, YANG datastore name and YANG Item
			Identifier for indexing; and YANG-Push subscription type and YANG
			schema name for a Message Broker topic naming scheme.</t>

      <t>Network node hostname, YANG datastore name and subtree and
      xpath filters are part of "ietf-yang-push-telemetry-message" 
      structured YANG data defined in <xref section="3"
      sectionFormat="of"
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message"/>. YANG
      item identifier are derived from subtree and xpath filters
      respectively from their YANG schema tree.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Conventions and Definitions</name>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", 
      "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to
      be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
      <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
      capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <section>
          <name>Terminology</name>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-nmop-terminology"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Network Telemetry</li>

          <li>Network Analytics</li>

          <li>Value</li>
          
          <li>State</li>

          <li>Change</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Message Broker</li>

          <li>YANG Message Broker Producer</li>
          
          <li>YANG Message Broker Consumer</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="Kaf11">Apache Kafka</xref> and <xref
        target="Pul16">Apache Pulsar</xref> Message Broker:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Subject: A named communication channel where a schema
          id is associated.</li>

          <li>Topic: A communication channel for publishing and
          subscribing messages with one or more subjects.</li>

          <li>Topic Compaction: The act of compressing messages in a
          topic to the latest state. As used with Apache Pulsar. Apache
          Kafka uses the term Log Compaction with identical meaning.
          </li>

          <li>Partition: Messages in a topic are spread over hash
          buckets where a hash bucket refers to a partition.
          
          </li>
          
          <li>Message: A piece of structured data sent between data
          processing components to facilitate communication in a
          distributed system</li>

          <li>Message Key: Metadata associated with a message to
          facilitate deterministic hash bucketing.</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="ConDoc18">Confluent Schema Registry
        Documentation</xref>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Schema: A formalized, documented structure that defines
          the shape and content of the messages exchange.</li>

          <li>Schema ID: A unique identifier of a schema associated to a
          Message Broker subject.</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="RFC8641"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Periodical</li>

          <li>On-Change</li>
          
          <li>Sync-On-Start</li>

          <li>Xpath Filter</li>

          <li>Subtree Filter</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-netconf-notif-envelope"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Notification</li>
					
          <li>Hostname</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="RFC8342"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Datastore</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="RFC7950"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Schema Node Identifier</li>

          <li>Schema Tree</li>
        </ul>

        <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
        target="RFC9254"/>:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>YANG Item Identifiers</li>
        </ul>

        <t>This document defines the following term:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>YANG Index: Is a subset of YANG Item Identifiers
          containing only schema node identifiers. Different to an
          absolute schema node identifier it includes the YANG module
          name and is therefore globally unique. When the schema node
          identifier points to a YANG list, then the key to that list is
          included.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Solution Design</name>

      <t>In order to identify which YANG node identifier of a network
      node YANG datastore is produced in which Message Broker Topic and
      Partition for which Subject, <xref
      target="yang_message_keys_indexes_solution">YANG Message Keys and
      Indexes</xref> are being introduced.</t>

      <t>In order to facilitate Message Broker Topic Compaction, a
      <xref  target="yang-push_message_broker_topic-naming_solution">
      YANG-Push subscription type based topic naming scheme</xref> is
      proposed. This segregates statistical (Value), State and State
      change YANG metrics and facilitates a YANG Message Broker Consumer
      to use the Topic wild card consumption method to select based on
      YANG-Push subscription type.</t>
      
      <section anchor="yang_message_keys_indexes_solution">
        <name>YANG Message Keys and Indexes</name>
  
        <t>A Message Broker MUST use a Message Key to index the message
				and a value to carry the Message content. If no Message Key is
        defined then the Messages are distributed in a round robin
        fashion across partitions. If a Message Key is defined, then the
        value of the Message Key is being used as input for the Message
        Broker Producer hash function to distribute across Partitions.
        Therefore, Message Keys facilitate Message ordering.</t>
  
        <t>The Message Key not only used for Message indexing at the
        Message Producer but also at the Message Broker for topic
        compaction.</t>

        <t>For YANG, the network node hostname, from which YANG
        datastore the YANG metrics are published from and the YANG
        index is used to generate the Message Key.</t>
  
        <section>
          <name>YANG Message Broker Producer</name>
  
          <t>YANG data nodes are uniquely identifiable within the YANG
					schema tree. <xref section="6.5" sectionFormat="of"
					target="RFC7950"/> defines with "absolute-schema-nodeid" how
					absolute YANG schema node identifiers are being crafted
					locally unique to the YANG module.</t>
  
          <t><xref section="3.3" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC9254"/>
          defines how globally unique YANG Item Identifiers are defined
          as text strings.</t>

          <t><xref section="3.6" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC8641"/>
          defines how YANG data nodes can be subscribed with subtree and
          xpath selection filters. A YANG-Push publisher publishes with
          "subscription-started" state notifications for each
          subscription which filter and filter type is being used to
          the YANG-Push receiver.</t>

          <t>To calculate the YANG Index of the Message Key, the YANG
          item identifier needs to be extracted from the used YANG-Push
          subtree or xpath subscription filter. If the YANG item
          identifier is a YANG list as defined in <xref section="7.8"
          sectionFormat="of" target="RFC7950"/> the YANG list key
          defined in <xref section="7.8.2" sectionFormat="of"
          target="RFC7950"/> statement is suffixed with a "/" to the
          YANG Item Identifier. </t>
        
          <t>For example, if the following xpath filter is being used, 
          the YANG Item Identifier is 
          "ietf-interface:interfaces/interface". Interface is a YANG
          list with name as key. Therefore, the YANG Index of the
          Message Key is "ietf-interface:interfaces/interface/name".</t>

<figure anchor="yang-push-xpath-filter-example"
title="YANG-Push ietf-interface Xpath Filter Example">        
<sourcecode type="xml"><![CDATA[
ietf-interface:interfaces/interface[type='ianaift:ethernetCsmacd']      
]]></sourcecode></figure>

          <t>For example, if the following subtree filter is being used, 
          the YANG Item Identifier is
          "ietf-hardware:hardware/component/state". Therefore, the YANG
          Index of the Message Key is
          "ietf-hardware:hardware/component/state".</t>

<figure anchor="yang-push-subtree-filter-example"
title="YANG-Push ietf-hardware Subtree Filter Example">        
<sourcecode type="xml"><![CDATA[
<get>
  <filter type="subtree">
    <hardware xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-hardware">
      <component>
        <state/>
      </component>
    </hardware>
  </filter>
</get>        
]]></sourcecode></figure>
        
          <t>When the Message is being produced to the Message Broker,
          the Network node hostname and YANG datastore name is used from
          the structured YANG data defined in
          "ietf-yang-push-telemetry-message" <xref section="3"
          sectionFormat="of"
          target="I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message"/>
          where the YANG Index is derived from subtree and xpath
          filters, respectively from their YANG schema tree.</t>
        </section>
  
        <section>
          <name>YANG Message Broker Consumer</name>
  
          <t>The consumer hashes the Message Key and applies modulo with
          the number of partitions to determine the partition it needs
          to consume from to obtain Messages with desired Message Key.
          </t>
        </section>
  
      </section>
  
      <section anchor="yang-push_message_broker_topic-naming_solution">
        <name>YANG-Push Message Broker Topic Naming</name>
  
        <t>YANG can be subscribed periodically, on-change or on-change
        with sync-on-start. Periodical subscriptions are used for
        obtaining statistical metrics. On-Change subscriptions are used
        for obtaining State Changes and on-change with sync-on-start for
        obtaining States.</t>
  
        <t>Message Brokers topics are addressed with a unique name.
        Usually topics are named hierarchically similar to the DNS
        namespace where "." deliminates hierarchies.</t>
        
        <t>This document defines "statistics", "states" and
        "state-changes" in the topic name as the first part to denote
        the types of data. Followed by "yang" to denote YANG data.
        Followed by the YANG module names subscribed, and followed by
        the YANG Schema Node Identifier where "/" is substituted by
        "_".</t> 
  
        <t>For example, if the "ietf-interface:interfaces/interface"
        xpath filter is being used, the Message Broker topic name would
        be as following. In the example the project name and environment
        (prod, dev, test etc.) is prefixed.</t>

<figure anchor="yang-push-topic-name-example"
title="YANG-Push ietf-interface Topic Name Example">        
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
project.environment.statistics.yang.ietf-interfaces.interfaces_interface
]]></sourcecode></figure>      
 
        <section>
          <name>YANG Message Broker Producer</name>
  
          <t>For the Message Broker topic creation, the "periodic",
          "on-change" and "sync-on-start" contained data in
          "update-trigger" from "ietf-subscribed-notifications", YANG
          module defined in <xref section="4.1" sectionFormat="of"
          target="RFC8641"/>, subscription state notifications MUST be
          used to derive wherever subscribed YANG data is "statistics",
          "states" or "state-changes". The YANG Index MUST be derived
					from subtree and xpath filter data of subscription state
          notifications, respectively from their YANG schema tree.</t>
        </section>
  
        <section>
          <name>YANG Message Broker Consumer</name>
  
          <t>The consumer has the ability to consume with a wildcard
          denoted with "*" in the topic name to consume from more than
          one topic.</t>
  
          <t>For example, if YANG states should be consumed and indexed
          in Time Series database or stream processor than below Topic
          Name could be used, and the YANG data could be ingested into
          tables according to topic names and indexed per Message Key.
          If Topic Compaction is enabled, only current state is
          consumed.</t>

<figure anchor="yang-push-topic-wildcard-name-example"
title="YANG-Push Wildcard Topic Name Example">        
<sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
project.environment.states.yang.*
]]></sourcecode></figure>    

        </section>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Message Broker Implementations</name>

      <t>Topic, Partitioning and Message Keying are generic concepts of
      Message Brokers. There are two known Message Broker
			implementations supporting all features described in this
			document.</t>
      
      <section>
        <name>Apache Kafka</name>

        <t>Apache Kafka supports Message Keying, Partitioning and Log
        Compaction. The topic names are constrained to 249 character
        length and the following characters: "a-z", "A-Z", "0-9", ".",
        "_" and "-".</t>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>Apache Pulsar</name>

        <t>Apache Pulsar supports Message Keying, Partitioning and Topic
        Compaction. The topic names allow all characters except: "/".
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document should not affect the security of the Internet.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Operational">
      <name>Operational Considerations</name>
      <t>The YANG Message Broker Producer of a YANG-Push receiver should
      have three config knobs facilitate the features described in this
      document as optional:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Topic Distribution: Select between "topic" and "subject"
          distribution. Default is subject to remain backward
          compatibility to <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration"/>.</li>

          <li>Distribution Type: Select between "none" and
          "YANG-Push subscription type".</li>
          
          <li>YANG Message Key: Select between "enable" and "disable".
          </li>
        </ul>
        
      <t>To accommodate for potential date loss throughout the data
      processing pipeline, periodical update of the current State for
      State metrics is RECOMMENDED. This can be accommodated with
      YANG-Push as defined in <xref target="RFC8641"/> by complementing
      "on-change sync on start" subscriptions with periodical
      subscriptions. Alternatively, in YANG-Push Lite defined in
      <xref section="7.6" sectionFormat="of"
      target="I-D.wilton-netconf-yang-push-lite"/> this simplified in
      one subscription.</t>      
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
  
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7950.xml"/>
  
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8342.xml"/>
  
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8641.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9254.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-nmop-terminology.xml"/>
  
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-nmop-message-broker-telemetry-message.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netconf-notif-envelope.xml"/>
      </references>
 
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.wilton-netconf-yang-push-lite.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="Mar24"
                   target="https://arxiv.org/html/2402.06511v1">
          <front>
            <title>Toward Building a Semantic Network Inventory for Model-Driven Telemetry</title>
  
            <author fullname="Ignacio D. Martinez-Casanueva" surname="D. Martinez-Casanueva"/>
            <author fullname="Daniel Gonzalez-Sanchez" surname="Gonzalez-Sanchez"/>
            <author fullname="Luis Bellido" surname="Bellido"/>
            <author fullname="David Fernandez" surname="Fernandez"/>
            <author fullname="Diego R. Lopez" surname="Lopez"/>            
  
            <date month="February" year="2024"/>
          </front>
  
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/MCOM.001.2200222"/>
  
          <refcontent>IEEE</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Bod24"
                   target="https://arxiv.org/html/2302.01713v4">
          <front>
            <title>Toward Avoiding the Data Mess: Industry Insights From Data Mesh Implementations</title>
  
            <author fullname="Jan Bode" surname="Bode"/>
            <author fullname="Niklas Kühl" surname="Kühl"/>
            <author fullname="Dominik Kreuzberger" surname="Kreuzberger"/>
            <author fullname="Carsten Holtmann" surname="Holtmann"/>      
  
            <date month="January" year="2024"/>
          </front>
  
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/ACCESS.2024.3417291"/>
  
          <refcontent>IEEE</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Deh22"
                   target="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/data-mesh/9781492092384/">
          <front>
            <title>Data Mesh</title>
  
            <author fullname="Zhamak Dehghani" initials="Z." surname="Dehghani"/>
  
            <date month="March" year="2022"/>
          </front>
  
          <seriesInfo name="ISBN" value="9781492092391"/>
  
          <refcontent>O'Reilly Media</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Kim96"
                   target="https://www.kimballgroup.com/data-warehouse-business-intelligence-resources/books/data-warehouse-dw-toolkit/">
          <front>
            <title>The Data Warehouse Toolkit</title>
  
            <author fullname="Ralph Kimball" surname="Kimball"/>
            <author fullname="Margy Ross" surname="Ross"/>
  
            <date year="1996"/>
          </front>
  
          <seriesInfo name="ISBN" value="9781118530801"/>
  
          <refcontent>Wiley</refcontent>
        </reference>
  
        <reference anchor="Kaf11" target="https://kafka.apache.org/">
          <front>
            <title>Apache Kafka</title>
  
            <author fullname="Neha Narkhede" initials="N." surname="Narkhede"/>
  
            <date month="January" year="2011"/>
          </front>
  
          <refcontent>Apache Software Foundation</refcontent>
        </reference>
  
        <reference anchor="Pul16" target="https://pulsar.apache.org/">
          <front>
            <title>Apache Pulsar</title>
  
            <author fullname="Sijie Guo" initials="S." surname="Guo"/>
   
            <author fullname="Matteo  Merli" initials="M." surname="Merli"/>
  
            <date month="January" year="2016"/>
          </front>
  
          <refcontent>Apache Software Foundation</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="ConDoc18"
                   target="https://docs.confluent.io/platform/current/schema-registry/">
          <front>
            <title>Confluent Schema Registry Documentation</title>
  
            <author fullname="Robert Yokota " initials="R." surname="Yokota"/>
  
            <date month="December" year="2018"/>
          </front>

          <refcontent>Confluent Community and Apache Software
          Foundation</refcontent>
        </reference>     
      </references>
    </references>
    
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Thanks to</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Contributors" numbered="false">
      <name>Contributors</name>
      <t>We like to thank Victor Lopez for the initial idea on the
      network controller use case. Ashley Woods, Sivakumar
      Sundaravadivel and Rafael Julio for the idea of grouping topics by
      YANG-Push subscription type and insisting that Topic Compaction
      is a key enabler for inventory metrics and YANG data consumer
      integration and should be supported day 1. And Nigel Davis for
      confirming that Topic Compaction simplifies indeed data processing
      system architecture.</t>
    </section>
    
 </back>
</rfc>
